Finding Aid for Richard L. Weaver papers, 1937-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard L. Weaver papers 1937-1964
Weaver, Richard L. (Richard Lee), 1911-1964.
6 linear feet
85551 Aa 2
Professor of conservation and conservation education at the University of Michigan. Professional papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1966, and was the gift of Mrs. Richard L. Weaver (donor no. 4434 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard L. Weaver was a graduate of Pennsylvania State College (BS, 1933). From 1933 to 1936 he was head of the Science Department, Maumee Valley County Day School, Toledo, Ohio. From 1936 to 1938, Weaver was a fellow in conservation education at Cornell University where he also received his Ph.D. He next became College Naturalist at Dartmouth College (1938-1942), then director of the Audubon Nature Center at Greenwich, Connecticut (1942-1947). He then became Adviser in Resource-Use Education for the North Carolina Department of Public Instruction (1947-1952), also serving for part of this time as Project Leader of the Conservation Project for The National Association of Biology Teachers (1950-1955). In 1952, Weaver came to the University of Michigan with an appointment as associate professor of conservation in the School of Natural Resources. Here he instituted new courses in conservation education, some of which were offered jointly with the School of Education. In 1960-1961, he served as a Fulbright Lecturer in Pakistan.
Dr. Weaver was the author of numerous articles for scientific and educational journals of ornithology, science education, and conservation education. He also edited the "Handbook for Teaching Conservation and Resource-Use" published in 1955 and was co-author of Biology, a high school text published in 1957 by D.C. Heath and Company. Weaver was professionally active, serving as president of both the National Association of Biology Teachers and the American Nature Study Society. In 1957 Dr. Weaver received the Nash Conservation Award for twenty years of leadership in Conservation Education.
Weaver died October 16, 1964.
The Richard Weaver papers relate to his activities as college naturalist at Dartmouth College; as project leader of the National Association of Biology Teachers' program to increase emphasis on teaching of conservation in schools. There are also files concerning interest in conservation education and his participation in conservation workshops and conferences in the United States and abroad in Pakistan in 1961. The series in the collection are Biographical/Personal; Cornell Fellow in Conservation Education; College Naturalist, Dartmouth College; National Association of Biology Teachers; Workshops, conferences; Fulbright Fellowship: Trip to Pakistan; University of Michigan; Writings, etc.; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Dartmouth College. College Naturalist.; Education--United States.; National Association of Biology Teachers.; Natural resources.; Pakistan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Camping.; Conservation of natural resources--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical and bibliographical materials (Box 1)
  - "Conservation Education at the University of Michigan" (author unknown) (Box 1)
  - Notebook: "A History of the Weaver Family of Penn's Valley, Centre County, Pennsylvania, 1741-1941" (Box 1)
  - Notebook containing mimeographed letters written to friends while traveling in Europe June-September 1960 (Box 1)
- Cornell Fellow in Conservation Education 1937-1938
  - Papers concerning Cornell University's Conservation Education Survey 1937 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary report of Cornell University's Conservation Education Survey 1937 (Box 1)
  - Field notes of conservation education survey trip 1938, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches and speech material given while on survey trip 1938 (Box 1)
  - Notebook containing speech outlines and speech material (Box 1)
- College Naturalist, Dartmouth College
  - Field notes of trip to Labrador Peninsula 1939, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers 1938-1941 [A-L], 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers 1938-1941 [M-Z], 12 folders (Box 2)
- College Naturalist, Dartmouth College/Extension Specialist in Conservation, University of New Hampshire
  - Papers 1942-1944 [A-Z], 24 folders (Box 2)
- National Association of Biology Teachers (NABT) (Box 3)
  - Conservation Project (Box 3)
  - Southeastern Work Conference on Biology Teaching August 28-September 6, 1954, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - North Central Conference on Biology Teaching August 19-30, 1955, 7 folders (Box 3)
- Workshops, conferences
  - Survey of Conservation Education report (Box 3)
  - Haven Hill Conservation Workshop August 4-14, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Department of Public Instruction. Committee on Conservation and Education (Box 3)
  - Tenth Pacific Science Congress, Hawaii 1961 (Box 3)
  - Conservation Conference for Representatives of Business, Industry and Finance 1952 (Box 3)
- Fulbright Fellowship: Trip to Pakistan
  - Working files 1960-1961 (unprocessed) (Box 4)
- University of Michigan Course Materials
  - Miscellaneous (unprocessed) (Box 5)
- Writings, etc.
  - Reprints of articles (Box 6)
  - Thesis: "Conservation education in some federal and national agencies in United States" 1938 (Box 6)
  - Speeches, lectures, and articles, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Portraits (Box 6)
  - Workshops (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - North Central Conference on Biology Teaching (Box 6)
  - Workshops (Gainesville, Fla.) (Box 6)
  - Resource-Use Conference, Chapel Hill, North Carolina (Box 6)
  - Workshops, Summer 1953-1956 (Box 6)
  - Students at conservation camp (Box 6)